<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_transient_seat_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2020 - 2023 Andri Yngvason

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol for creating temporary seats">
    The transient seat protocol can be used by privileged clients to create
    independent seats that will be removed from the compositor when the client
    destroys its transient seat.

    This protocol is intended for use with virtual input protocols such as
    "virtual_keyboard_unstable_v1" or "wlr_virtual_pointer_unstable_v1", both
    of which allow the user to select a seat.

    The "wl_seat" global created by this protocol does not generate input events
    on its own, or have any capabilities except those assigned to it by other
    protocol extensions, such as the ones mentioned above.

    For example, a remote desktop server can create a seat with virtual inputs
    for each remote user by following these steps for each new connection:
     * Create a transient seat
     * Wait for the transient seat to be created
     * Locate a "wl_seat" global with a matching name
     * Create virtual inputs using the resulting "wl_seat" global
  </description>

  <interface name="ext_transient_seat_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="transient seat manager">
      The transient seat manager creates short-lived seats.
    </description>

    <request name="create">
      <description summary="create a transient seat">
        Create a new seat that is removed when the client side transient seat
        object is destroyed.

        The actual seat may be removed sooner, in which case the transient seat
        object shall become inert.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="new_id" interface="ext_transient_seat_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager.

        All objects created by the manager will remain valid until they are
        destroyed themselves.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_transient_seat_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="transient seat handle">
      When the transient seat handle is destroyed, the seat itself will also be
      destroyed.
    </description>

    <event name="ready">
      <description summary="transient seat is ready">
        This event advertises the global name for the wl_seat to be used with
        wl_registry_bind.

        It is sent exactly once, immediately after the transient seat is created
        and the new "wl_seat" global is advertised, if and only if the creation
        of the transient seat was allowed.
      </description>
      <arg name="global_name" type="uint"/>
    </event>

    <event name="denied">
      <description summary="transient seat creation denied">
        The event informs the client that the compositor denied its request to
        create a transient seat.

        It is sent exactly once, immediately after the transient seat object is
        created, if and only if the creation of the transient seat was denied.

        After receiving this event, the client should destroy the object.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy transient seat">
        When the transient seat object is destroyed by the client, the
        associated seat created by the compositor is also destroyed.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
